all right the
worldwide web what is it where did it
come from Al Gore didn't invented by the
way that's an old joke nobody remembers
that the worldwide web was
created by the physicist at CERN let me
let them tell you here you go there's a
little clip I got queued up there are
100,000 computers connected all over the
world to deal with the data in fact the
worldwide web was invented discerned so
that physicists all over the planet
could share the
data okay so the worldwide web was
invented so the physicists all over CERN
could see the data they could actually
share the data and when you think of the
web that's what it is right it connects
a bunch of things it was so the
worldwide web very simply was created by
Tim burner Lee to share the data at CERN
and that's where they made it and
another interesting fact that a lot of
people don't know is that the web
fundamentally was created to replace
email um and this is actually going to
become very interesting later on in your
knowledge about web documents and things
like that when you learn about things
like the multitype internet Mail
Exchange mime and bunch of these things
that you may not care about now but it
is extremely interesting and almost
nobody talks about this when they talk
about HTML and web development and where
it came from from and blah blah blah I
find it extremely interesting even if
this video is a little bit longer than
some so I'm not going to get really deep
down into it but let me just tell you
how the web came to be so so we'll tell
you a story I like stories so the story
goes like this and I actually live
through this time right so once upon a
time raise your hand by the way if
you're an old fart and you're in here
watching this you're in the comments
raise your hand if you remember using e
email in something called udora or I
mean the very first use of the internet
before there was a worldwide web was
email email and there were other things
there was a thing called gopher which
some of you might laugh about now but
it's becoming popular because it's not
so you know corrupted by you know div
soup as you'll see you'll understand the
term div soup later I promise and a lot
of people um don't know that the very
most important thing when the internet
first came out was email and everybody
was exchanging email physicists
University students I was in the
University when that came out and we all
had an email address and my goodness if
you had if you had an email address if
you had an email address on your
business card you were cool oh my God
you were like the coolest thing ever you
know and you could say what you actually
put in I mean seriously people thought
it was really cool there was no
worldwide web yet right so so how did
people communicate so first of all they
didn't have to wait for a snail mail
which by the way way the Postal Service
in America had an active campaign to get
rid of the world the word snail mail
because it was pejorative and you know
anti-establishment and stuff you weren't
even bored so email was getting
exchanged and if you know what email is
a very very I mean I can break an email
down for you but it's we can do it with
our hands here so at the top of an email
is a bunch of headers they call them key
value pairs mime headers M IIM and they
are multimedia internet me exchange what
they are is a a key in other words a
word that's separated with a colon and
then after that I'm doing it backwards
but after that there is some value right
so there's a key and a value key value
pairs as you'll hear people say those
headers in an email would then go down
to a point and then you get to a blank
line and then the first blank line is
the beginning of the body so every email
has this stuff at the top right the
header and it has this stuff at the
bottom there's uset uset again built on
email in order to understand the stuff
that people are talking about in the
chat you need to understand email so
this entire thing the worldwide web the
internet everything all started with
email and this format for how an email a
text document was sent to the world
continues today to to permeate every
part of our system and when we start
talking about the terminal it'll be
really fun that's another video when we
start talking about how to use the
terminal you'll still see the influence
of the teletype machine yeah that's
right so it's kind of fun uh even if
you're not a nerd um to understand the
origins of these Technologies so that
you can see where they came from and
where they're going and where they might
go you know there's a lot of interesting
things there so this all started with
email and email has a header multiple
lines with no blank lines with key value
pairs separated by a colon and then a
blank line and then the body and
sometimes you know sometime much later
uh somebody came along and said we need
multiple parts we want to send multiple
documents in one so they created
multi-art which meant that the body was
broken up into multiple parts that were
separated by a delineator that was you
know set in the top now do you need to
know that to make a basic website you
don't need to know that but you need to
know that that the web came from email
somebody mentioned uset so um but I mean
yeah there's also AOL and copy Ser so
all of the bulletin board services are
pre- internet they they technically
don't count as Internet they were not a
part of the internet copy surve AOL all
that if you've ever heard of that those
are all they were great you know things
but they were technically you would log
into that bulletin board and it was
isolated from everything else so the
world we web was the first opportunity
to actually share data across servers
that you just stand up a server put it
on the internet and you're now a member
of of this worldwide web right so so
let's get back to the email thing how
did email get communicated right so you
would have you would have a program that
you this is important because this is
going to impact how you understand the
worldwide web fundamentally and you may
already know all of this stuff but I
just want to spell it out so when you go
to send an email now today you go on
your phone or you get you go to a web
page or something like that right but
when email first came out you had a
program that you use to write your email
right the program could be a command
line terminal program like mut uh or Joe
you remember pic or it could be you know
something like udora that's graphical
and it has a little text area um and you
know and and and there's Outlook you
know if you running outlook on your on
your on your computer at work for
example you're still kind of using that
old school idea of you know I'm I've got
a an application um that I am going to
write my program my email in and it's
not connected to anything I can just
write the email there and it's not until
I hit send that it goes someplace right
and that place that it goes is to a
server okay so this is probably time to
introduce two terms to you which you
probably already know client and server
right and these these terms you can use
whatever kind of pneumonic device to
remember them whether it's like a a
restaurant or something but a client in
a server is the basis for pretty much
all modern technology so knowing the
concept of a client and server um is
very very core to being a technologist
today um and we're we're this is the
first time we get to talk about it right
so when you had a udora email client
there maybe that terminology makes more
sense to you now maybe you've heard it
before an email client is something you
write email in it's not connected to
anything until you hit send and then it
will initiate a connection maybe it
maintains a connection the the state of
the connection you know whether it's
connected all the time or not kind of
irrelevant you have a client and you
have a server and you send something to
the server you send that that data to
the server and then the server says okay
I got it and it sends a response back to
you it says okay I got your email and
what did the server do with the email I
promise you this is important to
understand the web and I'm going to get
there so so when that email goes to the
server the the server in that case send
mail SMTP servers which I used to have
to maintain uh and they I ran in my
garage actually for a while those those
emails remember that thing about the
header and the body the header and the
body in the case of sendil would be
separated um and all of the headers
would go into the file system and we
haven't talked about file systems yet
but it would go on it would be saved
onto the hard drive of the server right
and the server was largely a thing that
you know you would log into from the
command line using a terminal um there
wasn't a lot of Graphics there it that I
mean the server is kind of an enterpris
kind of big thing that deals with all
the emails coming in and I'll tell you a
story if you ask nicely one day about
the time that I shut down the corporate
email server thinking I was turning my
computer off for the day ask me about
that story someday and why I didn't get
fired it's a fun story so um because I
was on a Linux laptop I log so the
server contains all of the email right
and um depending on there's big fancy
names for all of this me transfer agent
me you know what
um but ultimately you can just think of
this big computer that's got all the
emails on it right and it cues up those
emails and it it looks at the header
those headers that say where it's going
to go and it figures out where to send
it next now we are going to talk a
little bit about networking later uh but
right now just know that the email
address gives the server enough
information to know where that mail
needs to go next whether it's to one two
three four or five different hops before
it gets to a server that your your your
T you know the person your receiver the
person who wants to get it they can then
when they they have their client their
client they say they click a button and
said hey show me how the mail I have and
the at the time the client would log
into their server and say do I have any
mail and if it does it automatically
downloads the mail and anybody who's
used email today knows about this whole
synchronization thing if you're using an
email client app on your phone or on
your computer now since the invention of
the worldwide web all of this stuff kind
of happens on a website now you have a
instead of having a separate app uh for
sending email which you could still have
and I suggest you get actually by the
way particularly protop mail which we'll
talk about um to in order to do mail
securely um instead of having that they
have they have websites now you go you
go to the website and the website itself
is not really a site it's more of an app
right and that is your client that's
your web client even though you're
interacting with a web server so that
can get a little bit confusing but I
want people to to understand all this so
so Tim bernsley and and the Gang at CERN
are like you know what there's way too
much email going around and can you I
mean we still get emails spam today
right we get lots and lots of email um
we don't know what to do with it we
can't there was no filters back then you
just got and by the way email was
completely insecure it's to this day
it's still insecure in fact you can log
into an email server and spoof somebody
else maybe you've got an email from
somebody that wasn't actually from that
person right because security wasn't a
consideration when the world world web
was invented nor was it when the email
was invented unfortunately and and so
you know the very protocol for sending
mail uh at the time was completely open
that means anybody could put a from
address and send it to a person and and
we used to do this all the time we would
send Love Letters to random people from
other people even though it was wasn't
really them just to to be just a mess
with
them and it's kind of funny because when
you actually interact with the sendmail
server the SMTP protocol it actually
talks to you kind of like how you know
it's like hi hello I mean those are the
actual Communications um and it's you
know waights around for your body and um
you can it's just really fun I don't
hopefully some of you Geeks out there
will appreciate me going into a little
more detail here um because
understanding how things work is part of
the hacker mentality um it's part of the
technologist mentality and knowing that
that's that what what problem was email
solving the first problem that it was
solving was how do we communicate
without using letters and then the
second problem immediately became how do
we deal with all of these emails right
and you've probably been a been a victim
of this have you ever have you ever been
one of like 9,000 people to receive the
same email when I first when I I'm going
to throw my mom under the bus a little
bit here when I when I first showed my
mom email back in the day um she you
know happily adopted it and promptly
decided to send all of us on on the in
the family everything she was ever
thinking and and so we I had to like I
was like please don't forward me you
know that
thing so I was getting tons of spam from
my my mom and I'm like oh God and I was
like I can't remove myself from the list
because she's got my email address so
I'm hostage right who uses email in 2024
anyway way either right it's all about
the chat text message you could get
fired for using text message back in the
day anyway so you know so the first
problem that the first problem was how
do we communicate the second problem was
how do we control the communication a
little bit better and so they came up
with this thing called a News Group
which is basically a subscription it's
called UCP news but the format for the
stuff that was getting saved was still
email right so all of these little
emails were getting saved not to a
server but instead of sending your
instead of sending it to a person a
recipient you know one or 10,000
recipients at one time you would send
your email effectively um to a news
server and then that would go into a
threaded and people who know Reddit it's
so funny that you know they Oh you mean
like Reddit I'm like no I mean like uset
so uset predates Reddit by several
decades and this is you know all 2600
that's where people would go to learn to
hack and stuff it's still very the thing
in fact most people who go to groups who
go to look up News groups today they go
to um they go to Google Groups so Google
Groups is a web service that's in front
of the old school uset news groups you
can still use uset news groups probably
a bunch of old farts out there still do
but in fact the entire I think I think
Linux the Linux development is still
largely on news groups and and these
these these you know these email server
these news servers the the point is is
places like CERN they were like okay
okay well this email we want everybody
to see this email but I don't want to
spam everybody so they started
collecting the email you see where this
is going believe it or not I'm going to
get to the web okay so the next problem
was we need to be able to send
Communications out that go out to
everybody in a large group and we don't
even know who the members of that group
are right and there's another thing
called mailing groups which is where you
subscribe to the mailing group probably
this still exists right and then you you
get you when when the email gets sent to
that mail to that news server to that
mail group server that server will then
spam everybody on behalf of the people
that have subscribed to that but there
are many variations on that the other
one is you know a news server itself
which could be an email client or a news
client and you would publish a thing
just like Reddit and you would have a
threaded conversation and this thing
about threaded conversation email is
going to come up all the time in this
convers we're going to when we go back
to markdown markdown was invented to
basically make it easier to take that
email and turn it into a web page so
spoiler alert there um so you have this
new server that's got all of these these
essentially emails right if you were to
open one of them up on the server you
would see the same thing that you would
see on a male server you'd see the
header and you'd see the body right and
you might see um yeah IRC IRC is a
different thing alog together um but it
is worth mentioning since you mentioned
it so at the same time that that email
was being invented as a sort of you know
not immediate method of communicating in
other words I'm going to send you an
email I live in France I I'll read the
email in America when I'm awake right
that's email um but realtime
communication was also a thing that was
needed and that is when all the
messaging protocols came up and these
are not directly relevant to the web but
it's probably worth mentioning them so
you know the problem is how do we
communicate in real time uh without and
you know all the other costs and you
know bulletin boards aside you have
things like Internet relay chat which is
there's a central server and everybody
sends their little messages to it um you
know think Twitter size messages and
they would go there and then it would
get spammed out to everybody IRC is
still a very very valid method of
communicating particularly in the hacker
Community um but don't think it's
Anonymous it's not um there are ways to
if you want to get into hacking and you
want to be able to keep tabs on um what
hackers are doing IRC is one of the best
ways to do that because it's the most
Anonymous of all the messaging protocols
out there um but you know just be
careful so me basically IRC is like is
is like any other chatting I mean
there's a ton of messaging protocols now
and it's it's so funny because when we
use slack or or um what's the other one
WebEx or um icq yeah um there there are
a number number of messaging protocols
out there that everybody signal um
everybody's inventing their new way of
messaging one another SMS which is a
phone messaging system is totally
different by the way um there are lots
of like Dynamic real-time messaging
tools out there and um they are
unrelated to the web completely they are
unrelated to the web some of them
leverage web Technologies but almost all
of them are unrelated to the web they
might have a web interface that you can
use um just like you know email but but
fundamentally messaging technology is
not web related um particularly the
original ones like IRC and and things
like that so but those that technology
kind of kind of kind of came about at
the same time that the non-real Time
Communication kind kind of surface which
we're talking about with email news
groups um and um and and ultimately the
worldwide web okay so um these were fun
times
um so you know we're not going to cover
uh how to set up an IRC client or any of
that stuff um I still feel we might
mention it again when we talk about
building your your professional or
Personal Learning Network um having an
IRC account and and monitoring what's
happening in the IRC channels for
someone who's just learning I taught
myself web development by reading news
groups and IRC because there was no
other way to learn it there was not a
single book I would go to Barnes & Noble
every week and there was was no books on
it for a good two years and I was able
to get a job doing web development uh
being the web developer for fibernet uh
back in God when 1997 or something when
I had not even done anything else
because actually earlier than that and
because I had just gone to these news
groups and to these um these IRC and it
was about that time that the worldwide
web came about and I I'm going to tell a
story about the first time I saw the
world we I'm going to totally date
myself here so as many of you know I was
once upon a time uh I worked I was in
the Russian Department I I was at at
briam University and I worked in the you
know really world-renown language lab of
briam Young University that's
responsible for training all the the LDS
missionaries and their different
language skills as well as lots of
members of the CIA and other places like
that um and while I was in the language
lab uh there and I was you know writing
different language software and helping
people get to use their computers and
all that stuff um I was and using Adora
and gopher which is I'm not even going
to talk about it go Google it Google
gopher uh that used to there was used to
be big fights so there used to be a big
technology debate about whether gopher
or the web was going to win which one
was going to be the method of
communicating
collaboratively um about stuff which
thing was going to be the content
distribution system for the world for
Humanity and there people would fight
like tooth and nail Over Gopher versus
web versus worldwide web and um
obviously the worldwide web won mostly
because pictures honest to God mostly
because pictures and and I would argue
porn I'm just going to say it you can go
back through history and I porn has been
one of the things that has pushed
technology past all the other ones you
know anyway so we won't dwell on that
but the worldwide web came by I remember
I was I was working in the um the
internet's for
porn so the internet was actually
invented this is why I'm doing this
historical you know thing the internet
was not invented for porn it was
probably used by porn it probably really
fast for porn but it's not the way it
was created it was actually unless your
porn it was involved with you know
physics it was actually internet was
invented to to to save people from
getting lots of spam in their inbox they
could go out to a a they could go out to
a web server and they could see what so
and so had written about the latest
physics experiments and they could see
pictures okay that's really important
and yeah later that was used for porn
and and obviously we know what happened
there um but but if you think about what
what happened with the worldwide web
fundamentally um what it was was it was
a place to put all those emails and to
add pictures to the emails and to link
in other things there's another
technology that was emerging at the same
time and back then
um it it had a name and people said it
we don't even think about it now um so
we used to say um they're hypertext okay
so what is hypertext I'm going to do a
little search right here uh what Let's
do let's do a chat GPT search what is
hypertext let's see what chat GPT has to
say about this hypertext is text
displayed on a computer or other
electronic device with references
hyperlink
uh or other text that the reader can
immediately access usually by Mouse
click or by key press it provides an
easy to use in flexible format for
sharing information over the Internet
most commonly used in web pages so
hypertext was actually I I think
hypertext was a major fail actually as
after several decades of using it um
suffice it to say because links change
and content changes and links break and
they don't represent the same thing they
used to do but the idea of clicking on
text and following it to have it take
you someplace else um was still at the
core of everything uh that was created
in the worldwide web and in thinking in
terms of physics we can think of it as
being one person's experiment could then
be linked to another person's experiment
and I want to tell another story about
someone that I taught HTML to very early
um a peer of mine Doug actually hockey
player really great guy um he was
learning Portugese um and he was he
worked in the lab with me and I taught
him
HTML um he was in dental school and to
this day he's actually still really I I
need to probably call him up hey can can
you help me with my teeth uh he's still
he's still a practicing dentist in in
Utah someplace anyway um good good
friend of mine and and I taught him uh
HTML um that I'd learned you know by
studying these news groups and thing and
he was one of the first people oh no no
no no no no he wasn't he wasn't a
dentist I got that wrong he's
opthalmologist I remember because he
showed me pictures of people with
needles in their eyes yeah it wasn't a
dentist I mixed him up so it was an
opthalmologist um and anyway so he made
a website with um he he put this website
and he put pictures of a surgery eyeball
surgery and he was one of the very first
websites uh to ever exist and his his
site got pounded by other people in the
industry because he was like oh my God
he's like he was literally like one of
the only people who had this is way
before Google even existed and but that
story came kind of after but the other
story I was telling which is the first
time I was sitting I was sitting in the
computer lab and somebody showed me the
worldwide web I like well have you seen
the worldwide web yet and I opened up
something called um and I'll see if I
can find it here uh I opened up
something called
Mosaic and um this is going to be going
to really get me uh got it Mosaic web
browser
uh which you know I'm going to tell you
the history here so here here it is
here's what the Mosaic looks like and
back in the day this was the first
worldw web page um and as you can see it
was very simple right but I remember
having somebody show me this and showing
me this text that I could click on you
got to understand compared to gopher
this was like the fact that we even had
a picture was ridiculously cool and we
could click on this blue text and at the
time you were forced to use blue text
for non-visited links and purple text
for visited links and the original
designers of the worldwide web did not
want to give creators of websites the
latitude to change that information
because it would take away the
consistency for the reader in fact to
this day you on a Kindle a Kindle is
easier to read because the user has
control of the style and not the author
which remains a point of strong
agreement about the the functionality
people are and and as soon as as as
people started creating Netscape
Netscape create allowed people to do
backgrounds and things like that people
started creating really amazingly bad
80s websites um and this is just kind of
fun hopefully this will be we're going
to learn I promise but this is this is
just kind of some of the fun stuff um I
mean gosh look at look at look at all
these bad 80s websites here I mean this
this
this is the yell School of Art
um oh my gosh I mean it's there's like
so many bad 80s websites um you they
like there's actually Mr Robot used to
make fun of of the
websites and yeah I mean the 80s we I
mean they were so bad these are actually
really good what the hell uh there's
like 80s hair oh God
Cusack check her out oh my gosh
so yeah the bad 8s websites um but at
least there these aren't even
bad these aren't even bad man this is
like some of
the use dream weer yes we use dream wer
a single image back in the I know you
would wait you would literally wait like
like an hour to get one porn
picture like I I'm G to admit that I did
that I apologize if I've offended anyone
I definitely did that um so you know I I
I don't know God these are not even bad
some of these are really good anyway so
enough talk about porn in the 80s
websites and stuff like that um there
services for those sites yes um the
takeaway is that that you know the
internet went downhill really fast um
and the original scientific idea behind
it was that we would maintain you know
readability and hypertext and everything
and I believe it it it died in fact
you're seeing a lot of like if you go to
medium today by the way if you go to the
medium uh they're actually selling you
the opportunity to make 1980s websites
that don't have any any background or
anything because they want to simplify
it and have a clean interface so you get
the privilege of paying to do what you
could have done originally before they
allowed all this flexibility
um and yeah it's so funny because you
literally can only do like one bulleted
list and you cannot change the font and
you cannot all the links appear the same
way if you go to medium.com and you use
you they literally made a site that for
people to publish websites that enforces
the use of a consistent style so that
it's more consumable and I think this is
a really important topic um I cannot not
talk about this topic because because
it's so important to create a document
on the web and that's going to actually
lead us into other conversations about
what the web has become and everything
and I'm going to do a whole video on on
that right after this so the takeaway
from this is is quite simple my friends
you know the web started out as as a way
to exchange information without spamming
everybody with email and based on that
the document focus of the web which
we'll talk about in another video very
shortly um has remained consistent
throughout the technology
and and essentially a web server is a
place to put a bunch of emails that have
pick documents that have pictures
Associated or in or intertwin in link
with them that allows you to click on
one of those you know links those
hypertext links and go to another one of
those documents on the same server or
another server right that is what became
the worldwide web that is what we see
when we see Particle Fever here this is
a bunch of people clicking on different
links and looking at different reactions
and collisions and pictures of that or
or you know whether you're an
Opthomologist and so we get the
worldwide web that we have today um one
last thing before I leave on this video
if you have not seen Particle Fever uh
the documentary Particle Fever and um I
mean it's now two years old or so um I
highly recommend you watch it it's one
of the best documentaries ever made um
when I ran skill sec I gave people extra
credit um for watching it and writing
it's a simple web page about about it um
so many things have come to our world
through the through science through NASA
through CERN and things like that and so
the worldwide web uh which you know Tim
burners Le put together as a way to
exchange these documents in a way that
could be clicked on and and viewed
without downloading pictures separately
um that became the basis of what we do
every day you're probably you're
watching and including YouTube including
redit all of it it all started with a
bunch of scientists trying to figure out
how to not spam each other and be able
to just go see pretty pictures intertwin
intermixed with text on a server that
they could go to anytime so that's the
history I knew this video would be kind
of long um hopefully you fast forwarded
through it um but you're going to see
this documentation this document Focus
throughout the rest of this these videos
so I had to go there I had to show you
where it came from hopefully it's been
fun